<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Final Year Project Blog</title>
    <link>/Y4-Diss/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Final Year Project Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 12:42:50 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/Y4-Diss/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Log: Week 2</title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/week2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 12:42:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/week2/</guid>
      <description>This week I have been mainly gathering and reading academic papers surrounding GAs, Swarm Algorithms, QGAs and any research applying these areas onto routing or network optimisation.
I have started using Zotoro to keep track of any papers I have found. I am annotating papers as I read them so as to help me when I come to reference certain sections.
Papers Read:
 Quantum Genetic Optimization Quantum Genetic Algorithms for Computer Scientists  I have also started to write my project proposal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Log: Week 1</title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/week1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:42:50 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/week1/</guid>
      <description>This week, I have been primarily concerned with researching possible project topics.
I had originally thought I would like to do research into nature inspired optimisation techniques and their potential applications in the world of fully autonomous road networks. Whilst this is still an area I am interested in, and would like to research, it has been suggested to me that it might be beneficial for me to choose a topic more closely related to my supervisor&amp;rsquo;s field of study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/project_proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/project_proposal/</guid>
      <description>Project Proposal Sam Barrett, 1803086
Topic My proposed topic of research is the potential applications of genetic algorithms on fully-autonomous road networks.
Question Definition The question I will attempt to answer will be:
 What is the suitability of (Q)GAs with regards to fully autonomous road networks? How well could they perform and how feasible are they to implement over the next 1, 10 or 50 years?
 With a possible report title being:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/week4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/week4/</guid>
      <description>Log: Week 4 This week, whilst awaiting feedback on my project proposal, I have been continuing to research and compile papers related to my proposed field of study. I have found the papers predating the book I had started reading, these included very helpful definitions of how the road spaces were represented using a separate set of basis functions defined within the standard Cartesian coordinate system.
I have undertaken some preliminary research into language choice for the implementation phase of my project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/week5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/week5/</guid>
      <description>Log: Week 5 This week I have been focusing on preparing for my presentation. In doing so, I have found that I needed to research the real-world systems currently in place to critique and justify my research. I have been going through government publications to find data related to congestion and delays on UK Motorways. Much of the data is several years old so I may need to look to more general examples from other countries with similar systems around the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/week6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/week6/</guid>
      <description>Log: Week 6 This week I have:
 finished my presentation Recorded it Continued work on the background section of my report Begun implenting utils for my GA experiments, namely:  Road Network struct &amp;amp; functions mapping Cartesian space onto road coordinate system Plotting utils for drawing the road and placing cartesian points in it Structs encapsulating the phenotype and genotype of individuals Functions to initialise a population of size $n$ with a route between 2 points.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/week7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/week7/</guid>
      <description>Log : Week 7 This week I have been continuing to work on the programmatic implementation of my project. I have implemented population generation and the GA up to the selection phase. Performance of curve generation seems good, plotting is the slowest part by far and that would not occur in a deployed application of the system. I have been going back and revising earlier code as I come to learn nice syntax tricks in Julia such as the use of the piping operator |&amp;gt; and functional operators such as map, reduce, and filter which allow me to avoid ugly nested loops</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/week8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/week8/</guid>
      <description>Log: Week 8 This week I have:
 Implemented basic/ placeholder genetic operators These allow the algorithm to accurately learn/ approximate straight line routes from $A \rightarrow B$  Below you can see the population after 1 generation:
And the most and least fit solutions after 4 generations
Whilst in isolation this is not particularly impressive, in fact is under performs a simple Pythagorean distance calculation, it can be generalised and extended to avoid obstacles and to not intersect with other routes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Log: Week 3</title>
      <link>/Y4-Diss/posts/week3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/Y4-Diss/posts/week3/</guid>
      <description>I have more thoroughly read through a few chapters (6,13,14) of the book &amp;lsquo;On-road intelligent vehicles: motion planning for intelligent transportation systems&amp;rsquo; by Rahul Kala. Using these chapters I have a better understanding of the overall topology of the type of system I am looking to implement. Based on this reading, a rough outline might look like:
I have also found some public github projects where visualisations are made of GAs as they learn and are applied to the problem.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
